Paying close attention to something:
التركيز الشديد على شيء ما
Not that easy, is it?
ليس أمراً سهلاً، أليس كذلك؟
It's because our attention is pulled in so many different directions at a time,
السبب في ذلك أن دماغنا ينجذب ناحية اتجاهات مختلفة في نفس الوقت،
and it's in fact pretty impressive if you can stay focused.
وإنه لمن الملفت حقاً أن تظل منتبهاً.
Many people think that attention is all about what we are focusing on,
يعتقد الكثير من الناس أن الانتباه يتمحور حول ما نركّز فيه،
but it's also about what information our brain is trying to filter out.
ولكنه أيضاً يشمل المعلومات التي يحاول دماغنا تصفيتها.
There are two ways you direct your attention.
يوجد طريقتان لتوجيه الانتباه.
First, there's overt attention.
أولاً، هناك الانتباه الصريح.
In overt attention, you move your eyes towards something
حيث تحرك عينيك تجاه شيء ما
in order to pay attention to it.
من أجل أن توليه اهتماماً.
Then there's covert attention.
ثم هناك الاهتمام السري.
In covert attention, you pay attention to something,
وفيه تولي اهتماماً لشيء ما،
but without moving your eyes.
ولكن من دون تحريك عينيك.
Think of driving for a second.
فكّر في القيادة لثانية.
Your overt attention, your direction of the eyes,
اهتمامك الصريح، اتجاه نظرك،
are in front,
يكون ناحية الأمام،
but that's your covert attention
ولكنه اهتمامك السري
which is constantly scanning the surrounding area,
الذي يمسح المنطقة المحيطة باستمرار،
where you don't actually look at them.
حيث لا تنظر إليهم في الواقع.
I'm a computational neuroscientist,
أنا عالم أعصاب حسابية،
and I work on cognitive brain-machine interfaces,
ومجال عملي هو واجهات الدماغ الآلية المعرفية،
or bringing together the brain and the computer.
أو الجمع بين الدماغ والحاسوب،
I love brain patterns.
أحب أنماط الدماغ.
Brain patterns are important for us
أنماط الدماغ مهمة بالنسبة لنا
because based on them we can build models for the computers,
لأنه بالاستناد عليها نستطيع بناء نماذج للحواسيب،
and based on these models
وبناءً على هذه النماذج
computers can recognize how well our brain functions.
تستطيع الحواسيب التعرف على مدى الكفاءة التي تعمل بها أدمغتنا.
And if it doesn't function well,
وإن كانت لا تؤدي وظائفها جيداً،
then these computers themselves can be used as assistive devices
بعدها سوف تستخدم هذه الحواسيب نفسها كأجهزة مساعدة
for therapies.
للعلاجات.
But that also means something,
ولكن ذلك أيضاً يعني شيئاً ما،
because choosing the wrong patterns
لأن اختيار النمط الخاطئ
will give us the wrong models
سيعطينا النماذج الخاطئة
and therefore the wrong therapies.
وبالتالي العلاجات الخاطئة.
Right?
أليس كذلك؟
In case of attention,
في حالة الانتباه،
the fact that we can
الحقيقة أننا نستطيع
shift our attention not only by our eyes
تحريك انتباهنا ليس فقط عن طريق أعيننا
but also by thinking --
بل عن طريق تفكيرنا أيضاً --
that makes covert attention an interesting model for computers.
الشيء الذي يجعل الانتباه الخفي نموذجاً مثيراً للاهتمام بالنسبة للحواسيب.
So I wanted to know what are the brainwave patterns
لذلك أردت معرفة أنماط الموجات الدماغية
when you look overtly or when you look covertly.
عندما تنظر صراحةً أو خفية.
I set up an experiment for that.
أعددت تجربة لذلك.
In this experiment there are two flickering squares,
تحتوي هذه التجربة على مربعين يومضان،
one of them flickering at a slower rate than the other one.
أحدهما يومض بمعدل أقل من الآخر.
Depending on which of these flickers you are paying attention to,
استنادً على أي من هذه الومضات توليها انتباهك،
certain parts of your brain will start resonating in the same rate
ستبدأ أجزاء معينة في دماغك بالاستجابة بنفس المعدل
as that flickering rate.
بما يساوي معدل الوميض.
So by analyzing your brain signals,
لذلك، عن طريق تحليل إشارات دماغك،
we can track where exactly you are watching
نستطيع تتبع أين تنظر بالتحديد
or you are paying attention to.
أو أين تركز انتباهك.
So to see what happens in your brain when you pay overt attention,
لذلك، من أجل معرفة ما يحدث في دماغك عندما تنتبه على نحو صريح،
I asked people to look directly in one of the squares
طلبت من المشاركين أن ينظروا مباشرة إلى أحد المربعات
and pay attention to it.
ويركزوا انتباههم عليه.
In this case, not surprisingly, we saw that these flickering squares
في هذه الحالة، كما هو متوقع، وجدنا أن هذه المربعات الوامضة
appeared in their brain signals
ظهرت ضمن إشارات أدمغتهم
which was coming from the back of their head,
والتي كانت تأتي من مؤخرة رؤوسهم،
which is responsible for the processing of your visual information.
وهي المنطقة المسؤولة عن معالجة معلوماتك المرئية.
But I was really interested
ولكنني كنت مهتماً حقاً
to see what happens in your brain when you pay covert attention.
بمعرفة ما يحدث في دماغك عندما تولي اهتماماً خفياً.
So this time I asked people to look in the middle of the screen
لذا، في هذه المرة طلبت من المشاركين أن ينظروا إلى منتصف الشاشة
and without moving their eyes,
ومن دون تحريك أعينهم،
to pay attention to either of these squares.
وأن يولوا اهتماماً بأي من هذه المربعات.
When we did that,
عندما فعلنا ذلك،
we saw that both of these flickering rates appeared in their brain signals,
وجدنا أن كلا معدلي الوميض هذين ظهرا في إشارات أدمغتهم،
but interestingly,
وعلى نحو مثير للاهتمام،
only one of them, which was paid attention to,
واحد منهم فقط، والذي تم التركيز عليه،
had stronger signals,
سجل إشارات أقوى،
so there was something in the brain
بالتالي هناك شيء في الدماغ
which was handling this information
يتولى أمر هذه المعلومات
so that thing in the brain was basically the activation of the frontal area.
أساساً، كان ذلك الشيء في الدماغ هو تنشيط المنطقة الأمامية.
The front part of your brain is responsible
الجزء الأمامي من دماغك مسؤول عن
for higher cognitive functions as a human.
وظائفك الإدراكية العليا كإنسان.
The frontal part, it seems that it works as a filter
يبدو الجزء الأمامي وكأنه يعمل كمصفاة
trying to let information come in only from the right flicker
يحاول السماح بالدخول للمعلومات التي تأتي من الوميض الصحيح
that you are paying attention to
الذي توليه اهتمامك
and trying to inhibit the information coming from the ignored one.
كما يحاول كبح المعلومات القادمة من الجزء الذي تم تجاهله.
The filtering ability of the brain is indeed a key for attention,
مقدرة الدماغ على التصفية هي أساس الانتباه،
which is missing in some people,
وهو الشيء المفقود عند بعض الناس،
for example in people with ADHD.
كالمصابين باضطراب قصور الانتباه وفرط الحركة.
So a person with ADHD cannot inhibit these distractors,
الشخص المصاب باضطراب قصور الانتباه لا يستطيع كبح هذه المشتتات،
and that's why they can't focus for a long time on a single task.
وهو السبب في كونهم لا يستطيعون التركيز لفترة طويلة على مهمة واحدة.
But what if this person
ولكن ماذا لو تمكن هذا الشخص
could play a specific computer game
من مزاولة لعبة حاسوب معينة
with his brain connected to the computer,
أثناء ما يكون دماغه متصلاً بجهاز حاسوب،
and then train his own brain
ومن خلالها يدرّب دماغه
to inhibit these distractors?
على كبح هذه المشتتات؟
Well, ADHD is just one example.
حسناً، اضطراب قصور الانتباه هو مثال واحد فحسب.
We can use these cognitive brain-machine interfaces
نستطيع استخدام واجهات الدماغ الآلية الإدراكية هذه
for many other cognitive fields.
في العديد من المجالات الإدراكية الأخرى.
It was just a few years ago
قبل بضعة سنين خلت
that my grandfather had a stroke, and he lost complete ability to speak.
تعرض جدي لسكتة دماغية، ففقد نتيجتها القدرة على الكلام تماماً.
He could understand everybody, but there was no way to respond,
كان باستطاعته فهم الجميع، ولكن لا مجال للرد،
even not writing because he was illiterate.
ولا حتى بالكتابة لكونه أمِّياً.
So he passed away in silence.
لذا غادر الحياة في صمت.
I remember thinking at that time:
أتذكر أني كنت أفكر حينها:
What if we could have a computer
ماذا لو استطعنا توفير جهاز حاسوب
which could speak for him?
ليتحدث بدلاً عنه؟
Now, after years that I am in this field,
الآن، وبعد قضائي سنيناً في هذا المجال،
I can see that this might be possible.
أرى أن ذلك ممكن الحدوث.
Imagine if we can find brainwave patterns
تخيّل لو كان بوسعنا إيجاد أنماط موجات دماغية
when people think about images or even letters,
عندما يفكر الناس في الصور أو حتى الحروف،
like the letter A generates a different brainwave pattern
مثل أن يولد الحرف أ أنماط موجات دماغية مختلفة
than the letter B, and so on.
عن الحرف ب وهكذا.
Could a computer one day communicate for people who can't speak?
هل سوف يستطيع حاسوب يوماً ما أن يتواصل مع الأشخاص غير القادرين على الكلام؟
What if a computer
ماذا لو تمكن حاسوب
can help us understand the thoughts of a person in a coma?
من مساعدتنا على فهم أفكار شخص مرمي في غيبوبة؟
We are not there yet,
لم نصل إلى هناك بعد،
but pay close attention.
ولكن أعيروني انتباهكم جيداً.
We will be there soon.
سنكون هناك قريباً.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)